<?xml version='1.0' ?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="new-applications">
	<title>Create new applications in Red5</title>
	<para>This document describes how new applications can be created in Red5. It applies to the 
		new API introduced by Red5 0.4. </para>
	<section>
		<title>The application directory</title>
		<para>Red5 stores all application definitions as folders inside the "webapps" directory beneath the 
			root of Red5. So the first thing you will have to do in order to create a new application, is to 
			create a new subfolder in "webapps". By convention this folder should get the same name 
			the application will be reached later. </para>
		<para>Inside your new application, you will need a folder "WEB-INF" containing configuration files 
			about the classes to use. You can use the templates provided by Red5 in the folder "doc/ 
			templates/myapp". </para>
		<para>During the start of Red5, all folders inside "webapps" are searched for a directory "WEB- 
			INF" containing the configuration files. </para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Configuration</title>
		<para>The main configuration file that is loaded is "web.xml". It contains the following parameters: </para>
		<section>
			<title>webAppRootKey</title>
			<para>Unique name for this application, should be the public name: </para>
			<programlisting language="xml">
<![CDATA[

<context-param> 
    <param-name>webAppRootKey</param-name> 
    <param-value>/myapp</param-value> 
</context-param> 
]]>
</programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Handler configuration</title>
		<para>Every handler configuration file must contain at least three beans: </para>
		<section>
			<title>Context</title>
			<para>The context bean has the reserved name web.context and is used to map paths to scopes, 
				lookup services and handlers. The default class for this is org.red5.server.Context. </para>
			<para>By default this bean is specified as: </para>
			<programlisting language="xml">
<![CDATA[

<bean id="web.context" class="org.red5.server.Context" 
    autowire="byType" />   
]]>
</programlisting>
			<para>Every application can only have one context. However this context can be shared across 
				multiple scopes. </para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Scopes</title>
			<para>Every application needs at least one scope that links the handler to the context and the 
				server. The scopes can be used to build a tree where clients can connect to every node 
				and share objects inside this scope (like shared objects or live streams). You can see the 
				scopes as rooms or instances. </para>
			<para>The default scope usually has the name web.scope, but the name can be chosen 
				arbitrarily. </para>
			<para>The bean has the following properties: </para>
			<para>- server 
				This references the global server red5.server. 
				- parent 
				References the parent for this scope and usually is global.scope. 
				- context 
				The server context for this scope, use the web.context from above. 
				- handler 
				The handler for this scope (see below). 
				- contextPath 
				The path to use when connecting to this scope. 
				- virtualHosts 
				A comma separated list of hostnames or ip addresses this scope runs at. </para>
			<para>A sample definition looks like this: </para>
			<programlisting language="xml">
<![CDATA[

<bean id="web.scope" class="org.red5.server.WebScope" 
    init-method="register"> 
    <property name="server" ref="red5.server" /> 
    <property name="parent" ref="global.scope" /> 
    <property name="context" ref="web.context" /> 
    <property name="handler" ref="web.handler" /> 
    <property name="contextPath" value="/myapp" /> 
    <property name="virtualHosts" value="localhost, 127.0.0.1" /> 
</bean> 
]]>
</programlisting>
			<para>You can move the values for contextPath and virtualHosts to a separate properties file and 
				use parameters. In that case you need another bean: </para>
			<programlisting language="xml">
<![CDATA[

<bean id="placeholderConfig" 
    class="org.springframework.beans.factory.config.PropertyPlaceholderConfigurer">
Create new applications in Red5 
    <property name="location" value="/WEB-INF/red5-web.properties" /> 
</bean> 
]]>
</programlisting>
			<para>Assuming a red5-web.properties containing the following data: </para>
			<literallayout>
webapp.contextPath=/myapp 
webapp.virtualHosts=localhost, 127.0.0.1 
</literallayout>
			<para>the properties of the scope can now be changed to: </para>
			<programlisting language="xml">
<![CDATA[

<property name="contextPath" value="${webapp.contextPath}" /> 
<property name="virtualHosts" value="${webapp.virtualHosts}" /> 
]]>
</programlisting>
			<para>The contextPath specified in the configuration can be seen as "root" path of the scope. </para>
			<para>You can add additional elements after the configured path when connecting to dynamically 
				create extra scopes. </para>
			<para>These extra scopes all use the same handler but have their own properties, shared objects 
				and live streams. </para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Handlers</title>
		<para>Every context needs a handler that implements the methods called when a client 
			connects to the scope, leaves it and that contains additional methods that can be 
			called by the client. The interface these handlers need to implement is specified by 
			org.red5.server.api.IScopeHandler, however you can implement other interfaces if you 
			want to control access to shared objects or streams. </para>
		<para>A sample implementation that can be used as base class can be found at 
			org.red5.server.adapter.ApplicationAdapter. Please refer to the javadoc documentation for 
			further details. </para>
		<para>The bean for a scope handler is configured by: </para>
		<programlisting language="xml">
<![CDATA[

<bean id="web.handler" 
    class="the.path.to.my.Application" 
    singleton="true" /> 
]]>
</programlisting>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Logging</title>
		<para>
			<link xl:href="Documentation/Tutorials/LoggingSetup">Logging Setup Tutorial</link>
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>